Another crucial element of presenting style is how you use your voice: vocal emphasis.
Your voice can either support your message, bring it to life, and engage your audience,
or it can let you down and undercut it. Don’t let that happen. Warm up vocally.
What do I mean by vocal emphasis? I mean the music of your voice — not just the words, but the actual sound your voice is making.
Is it loud? Is it soft? Is it high? Is it low? Are you pausing?
All of these elements, the tone you bring. Think about how you might read a story to a child at bedtime,
how you might read a simple children’s story. You’d bring it to life.
“And then the evil wizard leaned forward and said, ‘Go down into the cellar!’”
You’d bring it to life. Now, that may sound over the top for a business context, but I want you to try this out.
Go home. Read your last business presentation as if you were reading it to a child.
Record yourself on your phone. Play it back. I bet it sounds more compelling.
Turn up the dial a little, explore, expand your vocal range, and you will engage your audience.
Does vocal emphasis really matter? Surely words mean what they say.
Think about this. What’s the difference between “I gave him a hundred dollars”,
“I gave him a hundred dollars”, “I gave him a hundred dollars”,
“I gave him a hundred dollars”? Same words. Different meaning.
I can imagine using those sentences to answer quite different questions. Did you lend him a hundred dollars?
Did you give her a hundred dollars? Did you give him a thousand dollars? Did you give him a thousand pounds?
All of those I could answer with those same words, but I would emphasize differently.
So the question of where in a sentence I put the stress, just using my voice, using the vocal emphasis, is crucial to the meaning I want to convey.
Again, play around a bit, and think about, when you’re delivering a presentation, what’s the message you want to land?
Where do you put the vocal weight, the vocal emphasis, that will land that message most effectively?